okay welcome to RX and fur on March 7th
2024 Andrew to you first thank you
sure yeah so um last we so we've been
following through on looking at the RX
and fur examples that they've posted on
their site at reactive Bays last week we
went over the coin toss example we got
to look at some basic Syntax for putting
together a model and generating data and
then running inference as well as
looking at some plots along the way to
see the results of the infer function
that's in the package so this week we've
jumped to uh under basic examples to how
to train your hidden markof model
example um and here this is getting a
little bit closer to active inference
now we're looking at things like uh
State Transitions and observation to
State likelihood
mappings um things that are getting a
little bit closer to uh what we find say
in the textbook and so um I think to
start does anyone have any thoughts on
uh for anyone who is able to kind of
work their way through the code and the
expl um explanation on the site anyone
have any kind of like thoughts initial
Impressions on what um what's going on
in there or or
otherwise one second just pulling up the
code Andrew I was uh can you hear me
okay yes yeah I was um uh quite busy so
I couldn't really get to the code
although I did manage to run it through
but I first tried to to uh approach the
theoretical part that that aligns with
this code and that took me to to uh
sanj's book I believe chapter
nine uh which you guys agree that this
uh must closely maps to chapter nine of
San's
book
okay okay
so I don't know was there more
discussion on that that we needed to
have before my stuff
partially
observable Markoff decision processes so
yeah I don't exactly remember nine but
yes that's definitely the closest from
sanji's fundamentals
book gotcha
gotcha yeah there was no um while I
think it's great to try try and find
overlap between the two yeah there was
no requirement uh for this particular
project to to cross reference with Sun's
work um although I imagine it's super
helpful we did have uh I noticed someone
posted a question uh in the meeting
notes
um they noticed that the Roomba example
was a little confusing because they
called the transition Matrix the a
Matrix in the State observation mapping
Matrix the B Matrix whereas um inact in
matrices in the
textbook it seems to be the other way
around
um and just I'll speak on that and just
say yeah
there's like as far as notation goes
from what I gather um yes
that versus like looking at a PDP or
even just an hmm in the textbook we have
like this is how we're setting up the
model and so we have our categorical
distributions per usual and deay
distributions play a role later um so a
lot of things are very similar but that
said like um X is being used to denote
in this example observations whereas in
much of the textbook if we see an X it's
usually referring to States um and then
yeah with the the A and B matrices just
seem to be like flipped right so so our
state transition Matrix is denoted by a
whereas normally it's in the textbook
it's B observation Matrix like mapping
observations to uh states where in this
example we're mapping the flooring to
different rooms in the place where the
Roomba is going yeah that's that's our
likelihood Matrix which is normally
denoted by a in the
textbook um Andrew can I have a quick
comment on that I'd think coming from
the engineering side me being an
engineer by training I know in the state
space area the standard convention has
always be X do = ax + bu U and Y = C CX
plus
du so I'm not surprised that people get
confused by the flip of the A and B
matrices um as a fact the um the Matrix
that matches from the current state to
the next state in engineering has always
been a and the Matrix that Maps the um
you know the state to the observation
has always been C so I can understand
that
confusion yeah I know that that makes a
lot of sense and I'm sure that a lot of
the work that's being put into
developing RX and fur and so on so many
folks are working in like a more
engineering oriented background uh it
would make a ton of sense to me to just
kind of continue using the
notation as it's been developed there
yeah so I guess for for us or anyone
coming for a more
active uh background yeah I can see
where the confusion would come up uh
just one of those little things to track
um able to just follow along with the
variables as we go yeah and that just
the remaining part I noticed from the
buyer lab side they seem to almost
always use X for the observation which I
found uh confusing too in uh you know
they being
Engineers uh usually Y is used for the
observation but they use x but I
personally think that comes from their
course in um Asian machine learning
where they started basically
and just have a x variable and then
gradually they expand that to to include
time as well but I've notic that too
yeah yeah for sure I'm so used to myself
to seeing like why is being your your
outcomes or
observation we have that in the the
active inference textbook as
well okay does anyone else else have any
thoughts or or questions about what's
going on in here otherwise we might be
able to just do like a quick run through
of what's going on in the
code I think from my perspective because
I was reading through so hidden marov
models are something that we utilize
quite often in
genomics um for finding uh different
regions on the
genome um and a lot of
times we utilize and maybe this is a
terminology thing as well I'm not sure
um it's been a while since I've done a
hidden mark off so I had to look up
somebody else's example um you have the
transition uh matricies the start
matrices and the emission
matrices and this
implementation um is a little bit
simpler than some of the stuff that I've
seen from like something written in
Python
and I don't
quite understand the differences between
the A and the B States in this um and
the C and the use the
categorical I guess function uh as I'd
call it in Julia um for the S not um is
there any Clarity on anybody able to
provide some clarity on what these
things actually are in relation to a
more traditional hidden marov
model and if you that's what if you
scroll down to the model specifications
itself the function of the Hidden marov
model not the generation of the test
data
sure so we're looking
here yeah so this is where it gets a
little bit more confusing for me because
the A and the B Matrix that are just a
and b Matrix um with an s
there I see the constraints are in a
probability form that we can use but I'm
not entirely sure haven't quite been
able to map it back to what it in a
traditional hidden marov model is
actually happening
here
sure um is thata s sore Theta is here
yeah is that
Theta yeah I'm I'm actually not sure
myself I've noticed in in other arcs and
for like examples and documentation you
can actually directly type A Theta into
like the code
um here
too um got to use a special backslash
notation uh at least in vs code
so
gotta
yeah here uh as far as I understand it
right so we're so we're defining the
model we're giving it some kind of um
prior specifications about A and B so a
being State tostate transitions moving
from one room to another B is like the
models or the agents the roomba's
ability to uh you know come into contact
with X data points uh floor here being
flooring and then being able to infer
I'm in uh s room um and so
sore Theta if if that's indeed a Theta I
well h i noticed the that's that's
giving you your prior isn't it your
initial prior that's right this would be
the initial state right and so you're
setting distribtion yeah and then so
it's it's being filled with ones but
then I I
this
yeah it's being filled with threes right
so categorical is just is just a
function they giving you to make the
code easy to fill those those
matrices and it's filling it it's
filling it with a uniform point you know
your uh your sort of initial prior I
guess that's the uh is being filled with
uh uniform
3s yeah
I think that's right and then um so
being able to have a categorical
distribution and a de using de lay
distributions just intuitively it allows
you to specify like okay for initial
States we know we're looking at States
we know there's a total of three rooms
and so we end up with this like
3x3 um a bunch of 3x3 matrices that are
that are doing the mapping and then
because it's categorical we can find
ourselves in a spot where we move from
distributions to actually specifying a
particular um output right otherwise
we're just staying in the realm of like
having a bunch of 33s everywhere um like
earlier on when we're generating data um
for my understanding here what this
random Vector is doing for example this
is taking like setting up Cate ories
where we have three different um
potential States and then here we just
draw from one of them and set it to a
one um so I'm I'm not I might not be I
might not be doing the best job of
explaining this but it's like actually
being able to go from a probability
distribution to actually being able to
say oh specifically this room or
specifically this observation it's what
is what's being
um
countered
so yeah I'm I'm 100% sure that's not a s
th but it is a s zero that's the way
it's rendered in my
notebook yeah that seems to be right
because whenever I just look at another
zero we have this like you know a zero
with a dot in the center I guess it's a
diamond if I really zoom in
similar looks almost identical right
yeah seems to yeah it looks like the
prior on a the prior is a based on the
Matrix I'm not even try to pronounce
that um based on what they're writing so
the prior there is the a which is there
sitting into just ones filling out a 3X3
Matrix with ones
um I mean the setting up initial States
the standard like the probability of and
I'm I'm going to try not to throw out
like different like X and uh Pi uh that
are more standard to this my
applications but the probability of x
given y essentially is uh the
probability that the hmm is going to
follow a path of Y and emits a string X
and I'm trying to and that's going to be
equal to the product of the emission and
the transition uh Mission and transition
probabilities like this is something
that we utilize a lot and I'm trying to
understand where the emission and the
transition probabilities are in this and
how that
probability and and I don't think that
this is like a onetoone mapping I'm just
trying to understand where these things
go in this math yeah definitely I mean
from from Reading like the explanation
here it looks like whenever we're
defining the model and giving it prior
over State
transitions this is like basically
equivalent
to um giving it like a uniform prior
like we're we're all ones like nothing
gets stronger preference like going from
living room to living room is a one
going from living room to bathroom is a
is a one like it doesn't know right
versus the reality that I believe we
actually Define the data there's like
you know one of these is um yeah
entirely z0 I think one of the rooms you
just cannot actually in reality in terms
of like a generative process you can't
actually go from um you know one room to
another in this instance like a
particular room to another particular
room so that's the difference here like
defining a generative agent where it has
no idea at first and then for
b um the reason why we have tens and
ones is that uh so tens are all along
the diagonal I'm not sure why the code
example has the second and third rows
like um tabbed way over here um but in
any case yeah um on the diagonals we
have 10 and the idea is um we're going
to we're assuming that the model does
have a pretty good good sense of mapping
the correct flooring right so I I
attempted myself to make some notes Here
of
what yeah and sorry for the you know
this probably looks like a lot but it's
like upper left for the B Matrix um
going the hard flooring is act in
reality the hard flooring is mapped to
the bed tiles are mapped to the bath
carpet is mapped to living like that's
the true um mapping there and so along
the diagonals these are all actually
correct and then all the rest has some
noise that's what the ones are if they
were zeros then it's as if the it's as
if the room the agent would be perfect
in knowing like oh no if I see tiles
then I'm definitely not in the bedroom
um no instead we have ones to know I
mean as and also as the question from
the notes pointed out like usually in
the in figure 4.3 PDP the B Matrix is
hidden State at T minus one to Hidden
State at T here that's describing the
observation of the
flooring to the to the mapping of the
Hidden State true location like tile in
the
bathroom so that's acting more like what
we would call an a
matrix yeah yeah exactly these are it's
like your likelihood mappings yeah just
mapping States the the
observations um Andrew I don't believe
there's any significance in the tabbing
over of row two and three I actually
corrected it in my code I think it's
just an artifact of some some tabs or
something that's the way I understand
it yeah same here I I just corrected it
it's
entirely just
formatting yeah yeah I found that to be
the case as
well what is the um that that I'll I'm
starting to grasp how that all plays out
I think that the straints is where I'm
maybe losing myself a little bit there
um that looks like it's the actual
equation that we're constraining the
variables to is that
right yeah so this is like you know Q
denoting like a variational posterior
that we're trying to infer and then
we're marginalizing out like
here this and initial part this is your
um joint distribution between the
initial State and your States but you're
marginalizing
out um yeah the the variational
posterior over a your state transitions
as well as B your um observ your
likelihood um Matrix your your
observation States mapping and they
claim that that
is yeah it's a dependency coupling that
allows the inference to actually be
tracked
gotcha like I personally am also trying
to kind of wrap my head around that it
seems clear that a lot of this kind of
modeling we're doing a lot of
marginalizing out so that yeah we can
render things tractable but I can't say
off the top of my head I know exactly
how that works um it just seems clear
that yeah often we're confining we're
defining constraints whenever we build
these
um so in all of this and I'll have to
just kind of noodle over some of these
our discussion here to work through kind
of the similarities or differences
mostly differences between the
two's the more probabilistic approach
that I understand via the
how I learned it uh in this approach um
so this is all essentially generating
the matrices that you need to go into a
hidden marov model um and well really
learning it it's essentially the um was
the Brum Welch style um that I'm used
to um of learning a
matrix the example and it doesn't look
like I I didn't see this anywhere the
example has has anybody tried to
actually utilize those matrices then um
to predict something that's
unknown yeah any know how to do
that well it would be it would be
relatively straight forward right
because I mean you're saying take the uh
learned the
Learned um
matric values and then just do a blind
you know generate a new data set based
on that certainly you could do it easily
if I got your question correctly that's
yes yeah so I mean to do it is easy
enough because then you just Define in
your model you you just copy those
matric matric values in and then you
it'll it'll generate data set all you
want
but so that yeah you could definitely do
that you could also do experiment to the
code yet you could yeah I mean you could
that would be straightforward you could
also do the experiment where you could
say well you know you know what the
generative model values are or the
generative uh uh system Mo values are
you know what the model values are you
can run both compare those the results
get distribution of the
errors you could do all
that well and I think the challenge for
me right now is that and I've read
through most of the basic examples on
conceptual level it they focus a lot on
using the infer function to
essentially learn from the data that it
is provided I haven't seen any examples
of then taking that learned data and
then applying it anybody found that in
the
examples I'll just keep maybe just a
question if you've looked into the infer
function does the infer function only
provide fast real-time inference or can
the infer function also include what we
call
learning kind of
yeah that's something I may need to just
look into the infer function a bit like
does infer capture all is it you know is
it like a cognition function and it
includ attention learning and the fast
inference or are there separate
functions that are called called like
for kind of within trial and between
trial
inference where the between between
trial inference would be called
learning just just just thought but
we'll
explore
okay yeah I've personally not made it
too far through the examples but it's
like I think in this this Advanced one
where you're like developing a a car
that's learning how to like it looks
like it learns how to use moment
and movement to actually like surpass a
threshold that it can't initially um it
looks like this example involves like
over 50 time steps it starts to
learn like it it does like policy
comparisons and then it learns over time
like how to get enough momentum to
actually like overcome a threshold
versus like earlier on in the example it
just I don't there we are like it can't
actually reach the goal because this is
where it's stuck right I I really like
these um these animated uh
visualizations but yeah I I haven't
looked into the maths yet and the code
for this yet though maybe we can move on
to this in the in the future to get a
sense of like is it actually learning
like how is it doing that sequentially
through iterations what are what are the
variables being finded here to do that
or track
that yeah I'm I'm sure we'll find
essentially question answer my question
here uh throughout this course um just
kind of interested in once we learn
something how do we use it in
unknowns um unknowns of the same data
schema at which point the infer function
develops you at the very least summary
statistics that you can do Downstream
analysis with from the data with that
initial
schema then but that's still not yet
this like um the kind of next two Vistas
are active engagement with the
data and then the second one would be
flexible or variable data
schema but if if you already second one
ahead oh
sorry I was just going to say because
and I think it's more concrete if I kind
of explain what I'm trying to think
through and how I'm trying to think
through it is if I learn um from a a
human genome from a human genetic
sequence the that this is the and this
is just the example the hidden marov
model for um
a
competitive reg trained a hidden Markov
model to identify these regions in this
genome now if I take that model and move
it to chimpanzee which is 99.9% similar
to us how do I use that model
to understand where their repetitive
elements
are if that makes sense yeah well in a
nonactive like hmme which maybe even
something you're using you learn the
transition frequencies on the human
genome from like let's just say
annotated repetitive regions and then um
anything that has
atcg
genome you can then roll out that
hmm to its genome um and you're going to
get a probabilistic assignment is saying
okay under the templating that we
learned from the human repetitive
regions of these kinds here's How likely
these are these regions are to be those
repetitive but then if there's another
kind of repetitive sequence in another
species of course you wouldn't be able
to detect it or if if there was a
variant it you know so it it's like the
confidence the the statistical
instrument that was calibrated on the
human repetitive
elements it would be a secondary
question how applicable was it further
further away F
genetically absolutely and conceptually
that's absolutely correct I'm trying to
get down to the nitty-gritty of if I
were to use this hidden markof and this
is just because I understand hidden
Markov Model A little bit better than I
do some of these other um models um if I
if I build the hidden Markoff model with
their example on a test data set now how
do I take that um that learned test set
and then do exactly what I just said on
a essentially another Roomba in their
example um like this Roomba is in a
different house but has this sort of uh
exact same behavior at least similar
behaviors then now how do I take what
I've learned from room number one Matrix
that I learned from r one and then how
do I plug that into the code to instead
of just learning something to actually
predicting how the Roomba is going to um
operate so in your example
would what what's different between
cases is it the Roomba or is it the
house because it would make a
difference I wouldn't be able to answer
that one um I'm just thinking from like
a purely code perspective how do I use
what I've
made okay house the the house is the
species and then the the flooring is The
genome sequences that we're observing
and then the different rooms are are you
know genic intergenic repetitive
regions intergenic regions are tiled
genic regions are carpeted and so so
we're we're feeling our way along the
sequencing data only be okay tile tile
tile carpet carpet carpet inferring what
part of the um what room we're in then
so the room so you train on that house
Human Genome then pick up the rooma move
it to a different genome now if that
house was like in the same prefabricated
neighborhood then all the mappings would
be the same so then that mapping that
you had what what they call the B Matrix
but what um is the mapping between
hidden States and observations like that
will exactly apply but if you moved it
into a house where the bathrooms were
carpeted and then like the living room
was
tiled it would be giving you incorrect
information
absolutely but that Matrix itself can be
can be calibrated on the known and then
you just that's the exact artifact that
you take out but then you you need
to pull out at least one layer to ask
like how adequate is
that in a new
setting absolutely um Andrew would you
do me a favor and go to back to how you
TR your hidden marov model I'm probably
not being
very uh clear um if you scroll down to
the posterior marginal for a the 3X3
Matrix the essentially the result
section of this yeah that yeah scroll up
there we go perfect so these are the
results that we generate this uh
posterior marginal for a uh and
posterior marginal for B if you now
Andrew if you'll scroll up to the
results my understanding is that this
results code I'm sorry one more up to
the infer yeah this my understanding is
that this infer function is essentially
building those marginal matrices
understanding from the data um I data um
what the what it the model needs to
learn what the matrices need to
understand so this is essentially the
Bram Welch um kind of approach to this
where
you're learning from data what the
posterior and or what the
marginal uh distribution is for these
matrices so that you learn your matrices
your um in my terms the or my
understanding the emission and the
transition
Matrix now if we were to then want to
use those matrices how do I do that do I
if I use the infer function it's just
going to learn again right or or am I
wrong you know if I if I give a data in
there uh instead of I data um what is it
going to do is the code going to
essentially build a new results model
train it um how do I plug in posterior
marginal for a and the posterior
marginal for B back into the hidden
marov model without the hidden marov
model having those priors these are the
new priors that it's going to have now
how do I utilize those
matrices in the way that you're talking
about Daniel the um moving it moving the
Ruma to a new house or to a new genome
how do I utilize that hdden Markov model
in this way so that I can then actually
do what you
said moving it to another
system I mean is it enough to just do
the inference to learn and then
literally take the snapshot
outcome it's like well we we we chugged
all the weather data there's a 80%
correlation between cloudy and gray now
we've just distilled it down to this
summary statistic VAR you know Matrix
and now we're going to use that Matrix
in another way so it's like just you
just take the mapping and then just use
that as
um
uh in a in a another part of the program
using generative model that that again
recapitulates the
Roomba um setting if it were another
Roomba or maybe um the Roomba was
scouting out and learning that
relationship in the room through a
thousand sensory samples and then you
just send the summary Matrix to the real
estate
agent yeah I mean you you could
absolutely there's a lot you can learn
from these matrices Alone um the summary
statistics
absolutely
cool wonderful I don't want to moan this
I think I got the kind of my
understanding thank you guys and also
let's maybe explore in in shared repo or
however people want to like let's try um
ID data J data H data and like what what
happens if if we just or just have three
different priors and then just do
iterate over three options or something
just to give a little like flush out the
space a little bit more what happens
when you go in with a looser prior or
what happens when there's you know
something
else absolutely and I'm working through
and I meant to do this earlier this week
I just out of time um I'm working
through an example um through a uh
bioinformatics algorithms an active
learning approach fantastic book um but
I'm working through some of their
examples using python using memor more
traditional way essentially this is the
book I learned from implementing their
examples and then I'm going to try to
bring that into Julia into this uh RX
and fur and see if I can make that
actually happen the same
way and I'll share that code um here
this this next
week yeah nice that sounds very
interesting
and I I I personally was playing around
just with like number of iterations here
um I like jumping to like a 100
iterations the the results are not like
dramatically different but you you could
guess
that they're different
um so we're just like trying
to yeah do typical inference like have
the model
learn like what's your a matrix what's
your B Matrix compare that to because we
get to see on the inside because we're
we're generating the data ourselves we
know exactly what it looks like
um it's up here
here are your
true right like your true A and B
matrices we're just trying to
approximate that using the
model not to be redundant I think I
think we're all pretty much on the same
page with with that how it works but
yeah worth reiterating
perhaps does anyone else have any
thoughts on the
code I mean it feels like we've been
progressively making our way through the
code actually um we're just a little bit
away from the you know the final plots
here which I believe pretty seem pretty
self-explanatory it's nice getting
familiar with the plotting function
though like
here P1 a plot we're like just putting
in the Sate the true States data that's
generated from uh the generate data
function we defined earlier we update P1
plot to also include the result State
inferences of the model then we have our
labels real and inferred and so that's
this this is P1 this upper plot real
thir um some slight differences here and
there but it's is generally accurate P2
is just grabbing from that result from
the infer function the free energy
calculation over number of iterations so
the default code they use
iterations
equals
20 there so we end up with we get to
watch the free energy being minimized
over time looks like it generally levels
out sometime around maybe the eth or 9th
iteration looks rather static from
there um on the on the free energy I
mean this is the key point that the
maximum evidence model is the least
surprising one rather than pursuing a
simple maximum likelihood or leloy and
approximation or any other kind of like
direct evidence maximization method free
energy principle suggests pursuing
variational free energy bounding of
surprise
that's what the every parameter is being
fit with this kind of common approach to
a loss function um the Y AIS is
arbitrary or kind of like locally
contextualized units so it's not like
110 units of of this Roomba free energy
is you know 77 units um they're not
they're not directly meaningful units
which is like why usually uh the
gradient or the Delta f is what is
discussed
and then I think just from this plot
like it is monotonically
decreasing um it's always going down but
then when there's um noisiness or
changes in the environment we see plots
where like free energy can Spike and
also um by analogy to the loss function
with neural networks like live stream 51
it's not clear like what it might
stabilize at 80 and then like another 50
iterations later is it possible it drops
down to another Plateau like that is
seen a lot in training other basian
models so especially if you're looking
at joint
distributions of more than one
variable it's possible that like it
could stabilize and then drop
again but in a in a really like in a
single you know small Matrix this is
probably stabilized and you could
confirm that like by doing the exact
basing calculation or by calculating
surprise and finding like now we're
actually near the global surprise Minima
but in a joint distribution there might
or where there's stochasticity or
environmental change the free energy
traces are probably a lot more complex
than
this sure
sure and I I suppose also just um more
basic thing like just to refer back to
what was being discussed like say build
up a Roomba stick it in an entirely new
room um like if you threw it into a room
where all of the observation state
mappings were different and so you have
like I don't know the bathroom has
hardwood floor and the ba uh living room
has has tiles and so on I imagine like
even though we've trained this Roomba
well enough we end up with our P our
posteriors we took those plugged them
into um being used as the priors for our
Roomba now like you know we trained it
to go through this house you put it in a
new house like you would see free energy
probably start to shoot way up because
it's saying you know entirely new um
observation State
Mings and another funny thing with with
um is like so you put it into a
different house and then all you saw was
the free energy trace and then again you
don't know what the numbers on the y-
axis mean so it looks like it's stay
stabilized you think okay we're doing as
well as we can in this new house but the
model could be doing terribly it's just
out of stationary absolutely
inadequate estimation level but it's not
getting better or worse from how bad it
is which similar to to like a linear
regression putting it on a new data set
it will find the line of best fit and it
and but you have to do diagnostics to
find out how how adequate is that line
of best fit like What proportion of
variance explained okay it went from 140
arbitrary units to 80 arbitrary units
but did it go from explaining none to
all of the statistical variants or did
it go from explaining like two to 3% of
the statistical
variance and then that's the you know
difference between statistically
significant
and conversationally
meaningful
yeah for sure so I guess it's so the a
takeaway is to just bear in mind like
these are arbitrary units and their only
usefulness is like kind of relative to
the model itself like okay I don't know
exactly what 140 means I don't know
exactly what 80 means I don't know what
that means in this house versus another
what I do know is that like there's
optimization going on here over time is
it work cost function like this is
decreasing and that's kind of the the
meaningful aspect here that we we can
take
away well and if you were to and my
understanding is if you you know you
apply this to another data set as you
say then you know you might see it
flatten out and you know kind of that
the the model is kind of reaching its
limit with how it's currently designed
in the priors that you're giving giving
it and it might be doing terribly it
might be doing great
um but at least you know where the limit
of the model is at that
point
yeah actually my own question here
because I've mainly just spent time
trying to kind of digest what's going on
in the um kudal paper um where we had
previously had a live stream think was
live stream 55 uh where they're going
over uh direct policy in France and it's
using the RX and for package here they
spent a lot of time talking about kind
of the the more recent history of
different derivations of free energy and
so we have you know we have expected
free energy generalized uh free energy
we have be free energy um is it the case
that the RX and fur package here like
setting you know we set free energy
equals true in the fur package so that's
what's being used for
optimization um is it Beth free energy
like it's it seems to be the case that
you can definitely use it in RX but I
don't know if that is the default um
like is is is that what we're doing
whenever we run this particular code the
How to Train Your Mark model um that's
probably the
case
ber I remember when we did 55 if you
looked into the cffg and the be or the
beroun
but yeah I'm not know
how but B do you remember any of
this uh sorry I wasn't following I was
putting in the
the posteriors for the transition
matrixes and seeing like put them them
in as the marginal which you start and
see if
the the free energy converges more
quickly and it seems to do that so I
didn't follow what you guys were saying
okay all all good just just like which
free energy
flavor is being used here generalized
variational be
a
I think they mentioned bet somewhere in
one of the the code
[Music]
BS because they do apply the the message
passing on the the factor
cph that's also why you need to add the
constraint the the yeah the
factorization
constraint uh but I think this is just
bad yeah also is it um the case that for
a simple like if you're just doing a a
sing single
variable it might not matter but if you
were doing like if you were doing um
iterative optimization or if you were
looking at graphs with
Cycles then the the the Beth matters
more yeah the generalized the
generalized free
energy I I this is just speculative I
think the generalized free energy is a
generalization of variational and
expected so generalized free energy
captures the kind of real time and the
prospective
Elements which is what enables it to be
used for the um direct policy inference
whereas the the bet is an
approximation
factorization um
technique but the generalized free
energy is is a generalization in
principle across VF and and
efe possibly even the
fef all those kind of alternative future
free
energies and I think the bet that free
energy is more in the um meanfield
space of just like what are what are
ways you can take a
node and then approximate its free
energy um given like for example Cycles
in the factor
graph but any any or multiple aspects
that we can like pull out to specific
questions then and and also especially
if it connects back to like the
documentation if we're just like oh it
wasn't clear in this part what which
free energy was being used or like let's
just ask bias lob get their put improve
the
documentation yeah
[Music]
definitely all right does anyone else
have any other thoughts anything they've
done um
as well as I noticed we only have about
five or six minutes left here um so also
any kind of discussion on maybe what we
want to do next or actually no sorry we
do have a looks like next week we are
going to hop to
that mountain
car example which is under
the advanced examples
here
this one this one should be fun um live
stream8 very early with Alex shance is
also discussing the mountain car
problem um I don't even know if that is
using
pmdp we can look back to the code it's
either using PDP or a non
pmdp python code form
[Music]
um especially if the um kind of the the
benchmarking and the set uping of the
mountain car is consistent with the with
like the open AI
gym formulation and it might
be those are like some of the best
contact
points to to you know share with people
who are familiar with those gym and
testing
environments again especially if we can
show some of these other Diagnostics of
the model like speed to convergence
computational resources
interpretability modularity so
on not just training like one big
monolithic neural network to to to do a
better car it's
like we can inspect the policies and all
these different
things
if if if someone or multiple people want
to prepare to like present it or to run
the code just add your name or like
write comments in that
section but thank you Andrew this was
this was awesome and very helpful with
hmm awesome yeah for sure what could you
tell me again the name of the what was
the reference number for that um live
mention I want to check
008 008 just like that yeah and that was
in the that was in the uh it's called
scaling active inference and so that was
kind of earlier on when it was like well
we could replace the Matrix with the
neural
network and it's was like well this
helps us address large data sets but
does it kind of remove some of the
analytical Elegance or is it really
active inference all those kinds of
questions just looking ahead p uh past
the mountain card I think the mountain
card that sounds really interesting I'm
sure it's That's a classic might take us
two weeks to get through it I don't know
but looking past that next one are there
any examples that that would be
accessible to us that move more along
the concept of uh self-organization the
potential of uh you know how how the you
know kind of the
full um marov blanket and individual
agents that have some self-organizing
properties are there examples that would
be accessible to
us that we might be able to look at look
at going
forward so like let's ask um Marco and
and bias loveb like even like before
next week or next week let's say hey we
did you know we did coin flip we did hmm
we're in Mountain car for one or two
weeks and then we want to look to a
self-organizing example and see if they
know cuz obviously the best the other
thing that comes to mind though is the
um controversial but impactful 2013
paper Life as We Know It by
friston which did kind of speak to that
self-organizing element now obviously
that was not written in RX and fur but
we
could look at the paper see if the
codee's
there email
Carl get the matlb code for for Life as
we know it and then you know do like
Life as we know it in
2024 in RX and
fur because that that that um paper has
and continues to attract a lot of like
the philosophical
discussion and then that kind of
frustrates um some of the uh people on
social medias because it's like no
you're looking at a version that's 11
years
old and they're like well you should
have told me if the theory changed and
then they're like we did we wrote a
paper about
it there's also a paper and I and I'm
sure uh you'll remember the authors
immediately but there was a a paper that
was done really about uh social you
really social media organization and
Echo chamber Dynamics and I think that
was in pi MDB yeah epistemic
communities yes epistemic communities
and that would be possibly another way
to go yeah that that that would yes yeah
so maybe one or two weeks with mountain
car um meanwhile we will be kind of
continuing to sketch out our own
projects plus emailing people we'll
email bios laab um check in with them
ask about self
organization and then we can um on the
kind of like reproducibility and uh
wavelength we can do there's the
textbook examples and then there's
epistemic communities in Python and Life
as we know it in
matlb and I mean we can just engage with
authors of non RX and fur
packages and just say as part of our
learning we're looking for we're looking
to translate your package into or your
your script or your simulation into RX
and
fur could you just double check and send
us the total versions of the
code and then like we could go from
there and then that that could be
awesome and start to bring all these
different and I mean that's one reason
why the models are kind of hard to
compare I mean how do you compare a
2013 model of self-organization in mat
lab to
paper you know in Python but not pmdp to
2023 in pmdp if for it's like they
differ in their implementation in their
system of interest in the phenomena that
are being measured so there's a kind of
like highlevel consilience under the
free energy principle
umbrella but then yet the models are so
disperate but when we bring them into RX
and fur and we start to look at how the
um the the um recombinations and the
composability of the the app models and
stuff like
that a lot of those pieces might start
to click
better okay I'm going to stop the
recording thank you Andrew thank you
everybody thanks